Dr. Matthew Lilley

http://mattlilley.com/ | info@mattlilley.com

Plasma physicist with more than 10 years of experience working in a collaborative multidisciplinary research environment, primarily on non-linear phenomenon, instabilities and dynamical systems. Passionate about pursuing fusion as a sustainable energy source for the future.

Education and Training:

October 2005 - August 2009 Imperial College London, PhD in Plasma Physics

October 2001 - June 2005

University of Warwick, MPhys 1st Class (89%, top of class) in Mathematics and Physics

Research Experience:

Imperial College London, UK

Junior Research Fellow

September 2011 - August 2014

Research focus - Fusion energy: Nonlinear modelling of plasma instabilities driven by energetic particles, electrostatic confinement and particle dynamics in systems with discrete symmetry.

Achievements:

- Published 7 peer-reviewed articles in collaboration with national and international laboratories, including an Editor's Highlight Physical Review Letter [8-14]
- Discovered a new class of high frequency Compressional Alfvén eigenmode instability on MAST [14]
- · Built PIC version of the bump-on-tail (BOT) fast particle code I created during my postdoc
- Optimised BOT (written in Matlab) and re-coded in Fortran, yielding increase in speed by a factor of 4, allowing an investigation of long-time evolution of beam-driven nonlinear waves
- Invited to lecture at York University [F] and UCL [G] and to present invited talks at national [H] and international [I,J] conferences on the non-linear evolution of a fast-particle driven waves.
- Fostered collaboration with industrial partner, Tokamak Energy, securing a gift of a £1M experimental device
- Constructed and costed a research proposal worth £1.6M involving negotiations with multiple stakeholders
- Coordinated experiments with scientists at CCFE and the International Tokamak Physics Activity panel to gather data on fast particle instabilities.

Responsibilities:

- Manage a personal research budget of £25,000 and a student research budget of £12,000
- · Supervise research of a PhD student, 2 Masters students and 1 third-year student
- · Manage and execute a personal research programme
- · Train postgraduates: lectures in advanced mathematical methods

Chalmers University of Technology, Sweden

Research Associate

September 2009 - August 2011

Research focus - Fusion energy: nonlinear modelling of plasma instabilities

Achievements:

- Built open source MatLab software (BOT) now used by several laboratories (https://github.com/mklilley/BOT) to study fast particle instabilities.
- Published 2 peer-reviewed articles [6,7]
- Invited to give a summer school lecture [C] and present invited talks at two international conferences [D,E]
- Received a highly competitive Junior Research Fellowship position at Imperial College

Responsibilities:

- Manage and execute a personal research programme
- · Mentoring and informal supervision of a PhD student

· Training masters students: lectures in electromagnetic waves

Imperial College London, UK

PhD student

September 2005 - August 2009

Research focus - Fusion energy: Compressional Alfvén eigenmodes in spherical tokamaks

Achievements:

- Published several peer-reviewed articles on both theoretical and experimental topics, including a Physical Review Letter [1-5].
- Presented prize-winning poster and oral presentations [A] at national and international conferences. Was invited to lecture at the Culham theory meeting [B].
- Organised the 2008 Institute of Physics conference on plasma physics.
- Engaged with MP to promote the importance of fusion to the public.

Responsibilities:

- · Manage and execute a personal research programme
- · Running problem-solving classworks for undergraduates
- · Mentoring a student with learning difficulties

Other Professional Experience:

Decoded, UK

Product Developer / Freelance facilitator

August 2017 - September 2018 / January 2019 - Present

- Creating new, and enhancing existing, educational experiences in the area of technology, e.g. blockchain, machine learning, data, code and quantum computing
- · Create hands-on tools to help bring tech concepts to life
- · Delivering the courses to non-technical audiences

Retail Insight, UK

Senior Analyst - Decision Science

July 2015 - December 2015

- · Created an algorithm in python to optimise price reductions and times in order to minimise supermarket waste
- · Provided informal training for employees to introduce mathematical rigour into their data analysis techniques
- · Presented results to clients

Level 8 Ltd, UK

Founder

November 2013 - Present

- Founded a company with 2 fellow physicists in order to fund our fusion energy ideas
- · Created a hybrid app called Squidler (https://squidler.com) using Ionic, ActionHeroJS, Redis and MongoDB

Self-employed, UK

Freelance Physicist, Tutor & Developer

September 2014 - August 2017

- Published a peer-reviewed article with international collaborators [15]
- · Taught maths and physics to students with a variety of abilities
- Designed and created a brand http://mattlilley.com/ for my services and for others (http://rchapmanharris.com/)
- Became Chief Technology Officer for <u>The Curtain Works</u>. Added new and extended existing features to flesh out the initial site design and took the site live.

Publications – Peer Reviewed:

- [15] Eriksson F, Nyqvist R M, Lilley M K, 2015, Kinetic theory of phase space plateaux in a non-thermal energetic particle distribution, **Physics of Plasmas**, Vol: 22, 092126
- [14] Sharapov, S E, **Lilley M K**, et.al, 2014, Bi-directional Alfvén Cyclotron Instabilities in the Mega-Amp Spherical Tokamak, **Physics of Plasmas** Vol:21, 082501
- [13] Lilley M K, Nyqvist R M, Formation of Phase Space Holes and Clumps, 2014, **Physical Review Letters**, Vol:112, 155002 Editor's Highlight
- [12] Meyer H, et.al, 2013, Overview of physics results from MAST towards ITER/DEMO and the MAST Upgrade, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:53, 104008
- [11] Sharapov S E, et.al, 2013 Energetic Particle Instabilities in Fusion Plasmas, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:53, 104022
- [10] Gryaznevich M, Svoboda V, Stockel J, et al., 2013, Progress in application of high temperature superconductor in tokamak magnets, **Fusion Engineering and Design**, Vol:88, 1593
- [9] Nyqvist R M, **Lilley M K**, Breizman BN, 2012, Adiabatic description of long range frequency sweeping, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:52, 094020
- [8] Lilley M K, Breizman B N, 2012, Convective transport of fast particles in dissipative plasmas near an instability threshold, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:52, 094002
- [7] Lloyd B, Akers RJ, Alladio F, et al., 2011, Overview of physics results from MAST, Nuclear Fusion, Vol:51, 094013
- [6] **Lilley M K**, Breizman BN, Sharapov SE, 2010, Effect of dynamical friction on nonlinear energetic particle modes, **Physics of Plasmas**, Vol:17, 092305
- [5] Meyer H, Akers RJ, Alladio F, et al., 2009, Overview of physics results from MAST, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:49, 104017
- [4] **Lilley M K**, Breizman B N, Sharapov SE, 2009, Destabilizing Effect of Dynamical Friction on Fast-Particle-Driven Waves in a Near-Threshold Nonlinear Regime, **Physical Review Letters**, Vol:102, 195003
- [3] Zhang Y, Heidbrink WW, Zhou S, et al., 2009, Doppler-shifted cyclotron resonance of fast ions with circularly polarized shear Alfven waves, **Physics of Plasmas**, Vol:16, 055706
- [2] Gryaznevich M P, Sharapov SE, **Lilley M**, et al., 2008, Recent experiments on Alfven eigenmodes in MAST, **Nuclear Fusion**, Vol:48, 084003
- [1] **Lilley M K**, Sharapov S E, 2007, Compressional Alfven and ion-ion hybrid modes in the deuterium-tritium plasma of a spherical tokamak power plant, **Physics of Plasmas**, Vol:14, 082501

Invited Talks:

- [J] 55th Sherwood Fusion Theory Conference, On the Formation of Phase Space Holes and Clumps, 2014
- [I] European Physical Society Plasma Physics Conference, Energetic Particle Modes from bump on tail to tokamak, 2012
- [H] Institute of Physics Plasma Physics Conference, Nonlinear wave-particle interactions in plasmas, 2012
- [G] UCL, Feeling the Fusion Burn, 2013
- [F] York Plasma Institute, Dynamics of a nonlinear resonance, 2011
- [E] European Fusion Theory Conference, Nonlinear energetic particle modes: from bump on tail to tokamak, 2011
- [D] 12th IAEA TCM on Energetic Particles in Magnetic Confinement Systems, Nonlinear energetic particle modes: from bump on tail to tokamak, 2011
- [C] ITER Summer School, Nonlinear energetic particle modes: from bump on tail to tokamak, 2011
- [B] Culham Theory Meeting January, Destabilizing effect of dynamical friction on fast particle driven waves, 2009
- [A] 50th Sherwood Fusion Theory Conference, Destabilizing effect of dynamical friction on fast particle driven waves PRIZE WINNER, 2009